You have to have a plausible reason to
go from A to B. Correct.
>> Exactly. That's the key of an SDR. SDR
standing for surveillance detection
route. You start at what's called a
kickoff point. You have to make it look
like you're running errands. Ersands
that are totally normal and legit.
>> What are some of the things that they
would do to stay on your tail, like
switch plates, disguises, what would
they do?
>> Oh, yes. And yes. And then in places
like China, Russia, you don't do a 2 or
threeh hour SDR. you do an 8 hour SDR
because then they're using infrared
cameras, helicopters and and then you
make what's called a provocative move
just in case the surveillance are so
good that you've missed them. That is
going to be where you finally get them.
I handled an asset, an agent uh whom I
did not recruit. He had been recruited
15 20 years earlier and so I inherited
him and he was probably I'm going to say
40 years older than me. Uh and I liked
him and he liked me and we both had like
similar taste in art and and he was
always chasing women and
I know and I know a lot about Marxism
and communism. I'm well read in Marxism
and he was a communist and so we would
debate what Marx meant about some
obscure passage, you know, stuff like
that and that was always fun for me. So,
I needed to vet him. You have to
constantly vet your your agents to make
sure that they're doing what they're
telling you they're doing. So, I said to
him, "Listen, when you come to these
meetings, you're doing a surveillance
detection route, right?" He goes, "Of
course I am. I've been doing this for 20
years. I said, "Okay, I just want to
make sure." So, I called a team of Sue,
special operations officers. We we had
him right there in the um in the
station. It was a very large station.
And so, I said, "Can you can you guys
put a team or two teams on him and just
make sure he's doing what he says he's
doing?" And they said, "Sure, because
then I can write it up and send it to
headquarters and say his vetting's good
for another year. No problems." This
guy, he lived in a northern suburb
and the SES called me a couple of times
during the surveillance detection route
and they said, "This guy is awesome.
He he took a cab
from his house
to this, you know, eight lane highway,
got off on the highway. remember he's 70
years old
and ran across the eight lanes,
leaped over the the concrete jersey
barrier, went to the other side of the
highway, and then hailed another cab
going in the opposite direction.
So, he gets to the meeting and I knew
like every minute of his route. He gets
the meeting and I said, "Did you do a
surveillance detection route on the way
to the meeting?" He said, "Yeah, it was
a good one." And uh I said, "What'd you
do?" And he said, "Just take my word for
it. I took care of things." I said,
"Well, what's that supposed to mean?
Because I need to know if you actually
did it." And then he said, "Yeah." He
said, "I got out of the side of the
highway and I ran across the highway." I
said, "Oh my god, do you know how
provocative that is? If somebody was
actually watching you, they'd say, "What
the [__] is he doing?"
>> And he said, "Nobody was watching me." I
said, "Okay." So, do you have to maybe
explain to people what an SDR is?
>> You're not supposed to
>> You have to have a plausible reason to
go from A to B. Correct.
>> Exactly. That's the key of an SDR.
SDRs are very, very specific. SDR
standing for surveillance detection
route. They're very specific. So, there
are a couple of terms that you need to
know. Like a red road is a big major
road that has lots of cars. So, if
you're on a red road, you can't possibly
tell if you're under surveillance. But
you and I and everybody else, we drive
on red roads every day, right? Then
there's a black road which is not well
traveled, maybe through a neighborhood
or whatever. So,
you start at what's called a kickoff
point. It could be your house, it could
be your office, it could be whatever,
wherever you happen to be every day. And
you have to make it look like you're
running errands. errands that are
totally normal and legit. So, you get in
your car, you get on a red road, and you
drive to the dry cleaners, and you
either pick up or drop off your dry
cleaning. Okay, that's totally normal.
Everybody does that.
Then you go from that first what's
called an SDR stop to the second SDR
stop. Now, the second SDR stop, you're
not going to get back on that red road
because you're from the area. You're
familiar with the area. So, you're going
to do a cut through. You're going to cut
through a residential neighborhood on a
black road. And you see if you drag
anybody in with you from the red road
and then you go to, let's say, a wine
shop because there's this certain bottle
of wine that you're looking for.
And then you make a note to yourself.
Try not to write it down, but the make,
model, and color of the car, the license
plate, just to see if you see them
later. The definition of surveillance is
multiple sightings at time and distance.
So, you see the car multiple times at
different places. Um, multiple sightings
at time and distance. different times
and different places, right?
So, you stop at the wine store, you buy
the bottle of wine,
and then you
make what's called a provocative move.
This is what's called they called it the
provocative phase where you stair step.
You you go a block, make a right, go
another block, make a left, make a
right, make a left, make a right, like
you're going up a set of stairs, right?
So,
normal people don't drive like that.
It's very provocative. If you're under
surveillance, you're going to notice it
then.
And then you stop at, you know, the
Jo-Ann's Fabrics and you buy, you know,
set of buttons or whatever. I don't
know.
And then you to go from stop three to
the meeting location, you do some
driving maneuvers that nobody would do.
You drive halfway down a block, you pull
in somebody's driveway, you pull out,
you make a U-turn. Then you pull into
another driveway and make another
U-turn. and you just do all kinds of
crazy [__] that
just in case the surveillance are so
good that you've missed them.
That is going to be where you finally
get them. And then if you have
surveillance, you abort the meeting and
you just drive home and you do the whole
thing again 24 hours later.
That's what surveillance detection is.
So it's just it's just if you see it
just more than once if you see the same
car.
>> That's the principle. It's more than
once.
>> Yes.
>> So what were like and you became a
surveillance detection instructor at one
point in your career, right?
>> I did.
>> Okay. So if you were either um if you
guys were tailing a trainee or um even
like let's say like a real a real life
opposition force that was tailing you,
right? What were some of the What are
some of the things that they would do um
to stay on your tail? Like switch
plates, disguises, what would they do?
>> Oh, yes and yes. They switch plates,
they switch clothes, um they put on
disguises, they'll put on a mustache,
they'll put on a wig or a different hat
or um some will jump out of the car and
start going on foot. And then maybe you
get out of your car and you go on foot
or you go on a bus or you go on the
subway or in high threat areas we'll go
into a parking garage and switch cars to
a rental car that's been prepositioned
there by another officer. So it gets
very sophisticated. And then in places
like China, Russia, Cuba,
um
you don't do a two or three hour SDR,
you do an eight hour SDR. Yeah, because
then they're using, you know, infrared
cameras looking for body heat and
they're using helicopters and cuz
they're going to catch the guy that
you're trying to meet and they're going
to execute him. So, you have to really
make sure that you're not being
followed.
Another example is once you leave the
red road,
um I I worked with a guy who got a
little bit lazy. He was a good officer,
but he but he got lazy. So, he starts
off at the embassy, which is in the
center of town, and he takes a red road
far north, and he goes to um to a
restaurant. There was like a TGI Friday
up there or something. Disgusting place.
And he stops and has a sandwich. Okay,
that's a legit stop. I wouldn't use it,
but it it's a legit stop. And then he
drives all the way back downtown again.
Okay, you're caught. You're caught. Cuz
nobody would drive an hour to go to a
TGI Friday in Hburg. Nobody. Right. And
then even if you even if you were under
surveillance and knew it, you wouldn't
be able to spot their surveillance going
back into the center of town because
it's another red road. It never made
sense to me. And sure enough,
headquarters dinged him. You have to
write a whenever you meet with a source,
you have to write three separate cables
at least. You have to write a cable that
has the intelligence that he gave you
that you need to have disseminated to
the analysts. You need to write an
accompanying operational cable with all
of the stuff that the analysts don't
have a need to know, but that your desk
officer needs to know. Like, ah, he
asked me for more money. Oh, he's
depressed because his wife left him. Oh,
he just got promoted. Whatever. the
analyst doesn't have a need to know for
any of that stuff. So th two those two
cables and then you have to write a very
detailed cable on your surveillance
detection route and that goes to counter
intelligence
and then CI will look at it and say oh
this this is this is bad. He went all
the way up to TGI Friday and then came
all the way back down again and sure
enough they dinged him and they said
don't do that again. If you were being
followed, you just blew everything.
>> What's up, guys? Thank you so much for
taking the time to watch the interview.
If you got anything out of this video at
all, please like the video, leave me a
comment, tell me what you thought of the
video, uh, tell me who you'd like to see
on the show. I really appreciate the
support. It goes a long way on these
platforms, as you guys know. Most
importantly, I have some excellent
interviews coming up in the future that
I'm really, really excited about. So,
please subscribe to the channel so you
don't miss any of them. But that's it.
Thank you for your support.